Juan Ruiz

Professional contractor

Willingboro, NJ - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Juan-Ruiz/1b2ed5d8808f5413

Be part of a team in which I can contribute to reach company goals with my diversified experience in the fields of project management, medical devices manufacturing & industrial engineering.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Professional contractor

Edwards Lifesciences - August 2015 to Present

Validation Consultant at Edwards LifeSciences, Dominican Republic.

- Review validation protocols for semi-automatic sealing packaging machines.
- Develop Engineering Specification for the Sterile Barrier system (Pouch) such as Seal Strength, Seal Width and Wall Thickness.
- Prepare and Execute Design Verification Protocols for Different Packaging Configurations.
- Use design of experiments tool to optimize the critical to process inputs parameters for packaging sealing machine to comply with product specifications.
- Review and update Standard operation procedures and work instructions.

Process Engineer

Micro Stamping - Somerset, NJ - March 2015 to August 2015

- Support electro polishing and electrochemical grinding processes.
- Use lean tools and techniques to reduce machine and process idle time.

Validation Consultant

Integra Life Sciences - August 2014 to January 2015

located at Añasco, P.R.

- Develop & execute validation protocols (IQ, OQ and PQ) for semi-automatic sealing packaging machines and tools and submit final test report.
- Develop & execute CSV validation protocols (IQ, OQ and PQ) for label printers.
- Use design of experiments tool to optimize the critical to process inputs parameters for packaging sealing machine to comply with product specifications.
- Review and update Standard operation procedures and work instructions.

Sr. Manufacturing Engineer

Stryker - Arroyo, P.R., US - February 2014 to August 2014

- Generate engineering technical reports for of pull strength of glue bond between coaxial tips inserts and tubes. Use statistical analysis to verify that process capability (CPk and PPk) are within process specification after process improvement.
- Work with corrective and preventive actions (CAPA) required by the Quality department in order to eliminate root cause of non-conforming reports (NCR's).
- Use root cause analysis tool (Fishbone, PFMEA) for products non-conforming investigations.
- Support production department with trouble shooting and equipment correction.

Professional Contractor

Stryker - Arroyo, P.R., US - May 2013 to January 2014

- Plan, create and execute protocols (IQ, OQ and PQ for equipment such as centrifugal water chillers, variable frequency drives, cooling tower unit, centrifugal water pumps and HVAC control system.
- Inspect contractors for the commissioning of HVAC equipment in accordance to building codes, engineering manuals and mechanical drawings.

Project Manager / Proposal Engineer

Claudius Peters - Dallas, TX - April 2007 to May 2013

- Perform integration management for the initiating, planning, execution, monitor, controlling and closing process for projects related to the material handling and process system of power plant and bulk handling industries.
- Develop project schedule and budget.
- Write detailed project progress reports.
- Review customer engineering specifications to prepare a written project scope and proposal bid in accordance to client's needs.
- Submit documents transmittals; prepare procurement documents, requisitions, RFI, RFQ, specifications sheets and bill of materials.
- Design material conveying systems for the cement industry, includes low pressure pipe sizing, exhaust duct for dust collectors and high pressure pneumatic conveying.

Principal Manufacturing Engineer

Baxter - Jayuya, P.R., US - October 2006 to February 2007

- Provide the technical support of the manufacturing process such as filling and palletizing of IV bags.
- Work on the manufacturing process to improve the product quality, productivity and cost reduction of the product.

Manufacturing Engineer

Zimmer Manufacturing B.V - Ponce, P.R., US - June 2000 to September 2006

- Provide process support, process improvement (new tooling selection, CNC programs optimization, etc.).
- Create/develop/edit operating control procedures (OCP's) or Zimmer Working Instructions (ZWI's) needed to describe step by step required instructions in order to perform the manufacturing process.
- Prepare capital acquisition request (CAR) for equipment investment.
- Request and execute engineering changes to machine CNC Programs and process First Article Layout (FAL) as require.
- Provide training to operators in the applicable OCP's, ZWI's for the manufacturing processes.
- Develop and execute validation protocols such as IQ, OQ & PQ for existing or new equipment (lathes, ultrasonic wash stations, electrical discharge machine and milling machines).
- Develop manufacturing area lay-out using AutoCAD software to improve process flow and set up new equipment or machine in the manufacturing site.
- Work with corrective and preventive actions (CAPA) required by the Quality department in order to eliminate root cause of non-conforming reports (NCR's).
- Request and execute engineering changes to specification drawings, documents, CNC programs and master routers.
- Lead transfer team of new products (Periarticular plates, hip poly cups, stem extensions, ITST nails) from Headquarters at Warsaw, Indiana to Ponce, Puerto Rico.
- Perform process validation for new trauma products
- Supervise outside contractor for existing facilities and new expansion building projects.

Assistant Project Manager / Project Engineer

Aireko Construction - Ponce, P.R., US - December 1996 to June 2000

- Managed teams of plumbers, pipe fitters & sheet metal duct installers.
- Supervise installation of mechanical engineering equipment (duct work, Chillers, air handling units, piping for water and gases & pumps).
- Review design architect-engineers' working drawings and specifications which indicate building size, general arrangement, final drawings and specifications.
- Perform air leak test to duct work and water leak test for piping.
- Review and recommend approval of mechanical equipment, shop drawings, and technical date submitted by contractors, ensuring conformance with contract documents.
- · Write detailed project progress reports.
- Design duct for small floor HVACs system.

EDUCATION

HVAC & Refrigeration

Lincoln College of Technology - Grand Prairie, TX January 2008 to February 2009

Master in Engineering Management

Polytechnic University of Puerto Rico - Hato Rey, PR March 2002 to May 2004

Bachelor in Science

Polytechnic University of Puerto Rico - Hato Rey, PR March 1993 to May 1996

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

SKILLS:

- Computer Software (Microsoft Project, Word, Excel, PowerPoint), design Software's AutoCAD 2013; solid works 2014, Minitab 17 statistical software.
- CNC programming & machining process.
- Excellent communication and organization skills.
- Lean manufacturing and six sigma methodology knowledge.
- Fully bilingual (English/Spanish).